{
  "title": "People/Events in Period 1",
  "description": "Name who or what this event or person is.",
  "questions": [{
      "answer": "Pueblo",
      "question": "a name for the Native Americans of the present-day southwestern US Pueblos were also apartment like structures make of adobe and mud that formed the \"towns\" of the pueblo people"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Chinook",
      "question": "Native Americans living in the Pacific Northwest of the present- day united States."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Iroquois",
      "question": "Native Americans found living in the present-day northeastern United States."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Algonquin",
      "question": "Native Americans found living over a large area from the Atlantic coast to the Great Lakes."
    },
    {
      "answer": "small pox",
      "question": "Infectious disease brought to America by the Spanish that devastated native populations."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Mestizo",
      "question": "A term used by the Spanish that referred to a people whose ancestors were both European and American Indian."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Zambo",
      "question": "A term used in Spanish and Portuguese colonists to describe someone of African or American Indian ancestry."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Columbian Exchange",
      "question": "The exchange of people, plants, and animals between Europe, Africa, and North America that occurred after Columbus's arrival in the Western Hemisphere."
    },
    {
      "answer": "encomienda system",
      "question": "Spanish System to regulate and control Native Americans. The Spanish crown granted Spanish colonists a specific number of natives for whom they were to take responsibility."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Christopher Columbus",
      "question": "1492, led a voyage to present-day Bahamas and claimed the land he explored for the king and queen of Spain. By 1504, he had made 4 voyages to America."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon",
      "question": "Claimed Florida for the King of Spain, 1513"
    },
    {
      "answer": "St. Augustine",
      "question": "1565 Pedro Menendez de Aviles established a colony for the Spanish that has become the oldest continuously-occupied European settlement in the United States."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Walter Raleigh",
      "question": "Englishman who sponsored the failed attempt to establish an English colony at Roanoke."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Roanoke",
      "question": "1586 First attempt by the English to establish a colony in America. The settlers on Roanoke Island, which is located off the coast of North Carolina, was managed badly and when an expedition with expedition arrived in 1590, the colonists were gone. What happened to the colonist remains a mystery."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Sextant",
      "question": "An instrument used to measure the angle between a celestial object and the horizon that became essential to navigation at sea."
    },
    {
      "answer": "joint stock companies",
      "question": "Businesses owned by shareholders that invested in exploration and colonization"
    },
    {
      "answer": "Juan de Sepulveda",
      "question": "Spaniard who supported the Spanish Empire's right of conquest and colonization in the New World. He also argued in favor of the Christianize of Native Americans."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Bartolome de las Casas",
      "question": "Spaniard who fought against the enslavement and colonial abuse of Native Americans."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Spanish Mission System",
      "question": "The Spanish network of missions in the New World established to bring Christianity to Native Americans who were required to learn the Spanish language, as well as Christian teachings."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Juan de Onate",
      "question": "Spanish Conquistador and governor of the Spanish province of New Mexico. In the Acoma Pueblo uprising of 1598 his soldiers killed over 800 Native Americans."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Maroons",
      "question": "African refugees who had escaped slavery in the Americas and developed their own communities in Brazil and the Caribbean."
    },
    {
      "answer": "African American Religion",
      "question": "African slaves mixed African beliefs and beliefs and practices with Catholic rituals and theology, resulting in the formation of entirely new religions such as Vaudou in Haiti (later referred to as \"voodoo), Santaria in Cuba, and Candombie in Brazil."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Astrolabe",
      "question": "Instrument for measuring the position of the sun and stars; using these readings, navigators could calculate their latitude (their distance north and south of the equator)."
    },
    {
      "answer": "Conquistadors",
      "question": "Spanish soldiers who conquered Indian civilizations."
    }
  ]
}